howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
today's guest is Stewart Kaufman one of
the foundational figures in complexity
science great to be here it's a
wonderful be told I'm a foundational
figure in complexity science ah true it
is makes an old man feel that whether
it's true or not Jim buy it's true at
least in my opinion if Stewart was
trained as a medical doctor but is best
known for his work in developmental
genetics evolutionary theory theoretical
biology and especially the emergence of
order in far from equilibrium complex
systems he was one of the first
generation of resident faculty at the
Santa Fe Institute he has won a number
of awards including a MacArthur Fellow
and is the author of several interesting
and important books his most recent book
is a world beyond physics the emergence
and evolution of life which we're going
to talk about today but before we do I'd
like to recommend to other of Stewart's
books his origins of order holds a
special place for me it's the second
book in the area complexity science that
I read checking my Amazon account way
back in 1998 it's both thick and dense
but it's amazingly rich in ideas and I
still use a lot of those ideas today
for the most important books I've ever
read tell you the other one I'd like to
recommend to our folks at home is at
home in the universe which serves as
both a good layman's introduction to
complexity science as well as explaining
many though not all the ideas from
origins of order in a less dense form I
thought that was great tips and you know
I get about a penny in a corner when the
book sells so I'm retired now at you
know it could become a source of income
there are actually good books the
origins of order is is really thick and
it's about 700 pages it took me 10 years
to write I'm glad I was younger I'll
actually love that book but that's it's
me but before we get started talking
about the specifics of your new book
maybe you can start off with some
thoughts on the overarching themes of
your career what's your career been
about
that's an interesting question you know
I mean everybody's intrigued if they're
asked a question like that what my
career has been about in a funny sense
has been finding interesting questions
what are the important aspects of
science it's finding an interesting
question people don't talk about it and
you can't get a grant for it was gonna
give you a grant to say I'm trying to
think of the question but I've done that
a number of times when I was about 25 it
had been discovered the genes turn one
another on and off by Jacque cobraman Oh
in 1960 which answered central problems
and evolutionary and developmental
biology and I wondered were there
classes of networks of genes turning one
another on off that's spontaneous order
and to ask that I invented random
boolean Nets and lots of interesting
stuff followed they can't exhibit or
they can be chaotic order or critical
and it's turning out the genetic Nets
are critical a few years later I was
wondering about the origin of life and
everybody knew about template
replicating DNA and RNA and I asked a
funny question I said well what if the
contents of nature were different and
you couldn't make nitrogen and carbon
but you could make chemicals would life
be impossible and my thought was that
just can't be true life has to be a set
of molecules that can mutually catalyze
one another's formation so I came up
with the idea of collectively
autocatalytic sets and roughly 50 years
later literally about 48 it looks like
that's right Joanna Xavier and Bill
Martin and disel Dorf have found a
collectively autocratic set of small
molecule metabolites in archaea and
bacteria from before oxygen was in the
atmosphere strongly suggesting that life
started as molecular reproducing systems
you might want to talk about it's
fascinating so I keep finding these
wacky things to think about and some of
it's now standard complexity the santa
fe suit in my early life if I guesses in
my 40s and 50s not better it was just an
amazing adventure and I've gone off in
other directions thinking about quantum
mechanics and and the mind-body problem
and how to answer to card 350 years
later
so it's just a sprawling mess great you
could do that right you know I probably
have had a similar model that though I
had a less grand level I've been in lots
of different businesses and
organizations and projects I'm one not
to let too much grass core under my feet
no I haven't had a chance to address
some of these grand problems let's hop
in and talk about a world beyond physics
a little bit but one theme that comes up
again and again in the book is the
notion that Darwinian evolution is
incomplete with respect to the origins
and evolution of life could you expand
on that well Darwin knew that that's
nothing new
a Darwin takes on the evolution of life
once it has started but he's silent on
the question of how life comes to be so
that's not me saying that Darwin himself
said it he said there's sort of no point
on speculating about that at the present
time in 1859 or 1860 he does say but oh
what if there were a warm little pond
with ammonia and other things what would
happen so many of us are thinking about
what happens in warm little ponds and
we're the ones who were concerned with
the origin of life Darla's would have
completely agreed that's not an insult
the Darwin at all oh don't don't you
also talk about the fact that at least
the biological implementation of
evolution has other things going on
significant other things going on other
than Darwinian evolution other ways in
which order is formed well yes my first
book my tome origins of order takes up
the theme that I don't think Darwin
would have minded this at all you'd have
been I think he'd have been delighted
there's a lot of self-organization out
there in which things spontaneously get
organized and you know why wouldn't
natural selection make use of that so
that's what my whole first books about
and that looks like it's true in lots of
cases so I could talk about that for a
minute
the biggest thing about the new book is
it says the evolution of life can't be
explained by physics alone so we should
really talk about that but just briefly
about self-organization so to get your
listeners on board just think of a
snowflake it's got six fold symmetry and
beautiful so
flex structure that nobody thinks
natural selection did that there's a
spontaneous orders and it's due to the
the space group of relevant oxygen and
couple hydrogens that make up the water
molecule or think of a quartz crystal
it's got beautiful structure now think
of a whirlpool world who's got structure
they're called dissipative structures so
there's structure around all over the
place if you take lipids and put them in
water like cholesterol they firm hollow
vesicles called liposomes that are
essentially the origin of your cell
membranes well didn't take selection to
food that's physical chemistry what I
was struck by who was on the one hand my
study of these random boolean Nets as
models of genetic regulatory networks
Jim they just have astounding order when
I first found it as I said fifty years
ago
well I was 25 I'm 80 as of a couple
weeks ago and knock my socks off and it
still does but that's the case of
self-organization not in the sense that
there's a cell for just a spontaneous
order that appears at the level of the
system of simple components here there
are just a bunch of light bulbs look to
one another training one or they're on
and off and all you have to do is make
networks with a thousand light bulbs
turning one another on and off and each
life up has inputs from two other light
bulbs then is guided by some rule like
called a boolean function like or or and
where or says I will be on if either one
or both of my inputs are on and an says
now both of my inputs have to be on so
you for two inputs there's 16 billion
functions like if a NAND and nor and so
on just make a random network with a
thousand light bulbs everybody having
inputs from two light bulbs and give
each light bulb a random boolean
function like order if those networks
turn out to believe with just stunning
order which I ran across and was
thrilled about when I was 25 and why
wouldn't evolution make use of that and
it does those networks are dynamically
critical and literally 50 years later
maybe in the last couple of years we're
gonna have good evidence so that genetic
regulatory networks are critical they're
critical means they're dynamically
critical critical
they're poised on in doing farmers of
lovely phrase on the edge of chaos there
between order and chaos yes that was one
of the big takeaways out of origins of
Warner's whole idea of criticality much
credit to Chris lengthened who did much
to discover it and hasn't been able to
pursue it for other reasons I want you
take a little aside here this is
something I know our audience is
interested in this idea that's
oversimplification but fruitful things
happen at the boundary between order and
chaos
well they do there's something else I
want to talk about Jim as we get along I
wrote down an equation about two years
ago that is utterly relevant to its us
now and it's not in my last book but
let's just talk about fruitful things on
the boundary between order and chaos so
an example is your brain is dynamically
critical and as I said genetic networks
are dynamically critical what happens in
such networks is that just imagine a
bunch of Christmas tree light bulbs
twinkling on and off in some pattern and
you can ask the following question if
you change a given light but right now
from on dog just transiently flip it
call it damage the color it purple and
now watch if any other light bulb you
know that's connected to it one two
three steps away does something
different than it would have done color
it purple that's called a damaged by
Dietrich Stouffer
and so you get avalanches of purple guys
and what Dietrich and others have found
is you get a lot of little out launches
and very few big ones so a bit of
mathematics if you plot this on a
log-log plot we all learn logs you know
in the 10th grade so 10 is 10 raised to
the first power 100 is 10 raised to the
second power thousands 10 raised to the
third power it's just the number of
zeros so if you make a log log plot of
these avalanches it's a straight line
down to the right and the steepness of
the thing is minus 1.5 that's called
dynamically critical so action so
critical networks do that and part of
what it means is one variable can
sometimes influence things nearby but
sometimes things far away so it's got a
pretty wide span of
control deep in the order regime if you
trigger a lightbulb nothing much happens
and if it's an accounting regime if you
flip one lightbulb roughly half the guys
change what they're doing do these vast
avalanches and that may be why it's
really good being on on this edge of
chaos or another thing is a fancy word
called Tresor entropy and it's roughly
how much do the variables now control
what happens in the future and that's
maximized in critical networks so let's
see we can think of some other examples
I think there's work that I know a
little bit about my wife Catherine does
I believe that this is true if you think
about birds flocking Birds try to stay
some reasonable distance from the other
birds they try to head more or less in
the right direction and I think that
bird flocks are dynamically critical I
think ant nests are dynamically critical
I'm not sure about this Jim but it seems
to be a general feature interesting and
now you know we have human artifacts
like the electrical grid which is known
to be on the edge of chaos if you had
made it too ordered to be too expensive
it made it too chaotic it wouldn't be
very useful right in fact some set of a
Institute folks have worked with people
Aragon National Labs and essentially
proven that the electrical grid is
inherently unstable and does indeed have
failures on a power-law distribution
which would lead us to believe that it's
somewhere at the critical rate right and
that's this interesting work that's
grown up what I did my first work got 50
years ago I made what are called
erdos-renyi networks
it just means you got a bunch of light
bulbs and you randomly connect everybody
and all I could think about is a random
wiring diagram Turin yay or a regular
lattice like you put everybody on the
corners of a tile and connected grid
therefore nearest neighbor in two
dimensions and I knew that this is
stupid there was something in between it
like everything but I didn't know what
to do well bear about seeing others and
Mark Newman developed and others have
developed a whole thing called Network
science in which you have some nodes
that have lots of things that are
connected to they're called hubs and
others that are connected to not too
many things and that's power law
distributed and a lot of people study
that be
they're resistant to damage if you if
you knock out the rear hubs you damaged
a lot but if you knock out guys that
aren't connected to what you don't
damage very much there's no literature
about that indeed and of course we're
finding in the social sciences social
systems that at least roughly power law
distributions are turning up all over
the place live dispute on how close they
actually are to power all distributions
but they do have that attribute deaths
and Wars size of traffic jams size of
company size of cities that are have
this similar kind of distribution seems
to be a regularity it appears again and
again in complex system does by the way
there's a wonderful book by Jeffrey West
called scale that your readers might
enjoy and in fact we'll be having
Jeffrey on here I think in November good
but look I want to touch you about if I
may about this this equation that I read
so let's do it because I am I think I've
stumbled across something is much more
important than I realized when I wrote
it down so I'm not much of a
mathematician literally here's what
happened my wife Kate and Jim Harriette
a friend and I were up at our my summer
home on a little island near Seattle
called crane and I wondered about the
following thing suppose I know there's m
goods in an economy at time T so M sub T
like M is 24 goods in the economy now
could I write down some equation for how
many goods would be in the economy at
the next time at M of T plus 1 and as I
thought something really simple M of T
plus 1 will be what we've got now M of T
plus and here's the central idea Jim
plus all the new things we can make out
of the 24 things you've got lying around
now so I could take any one of the 24
things and see if I could do something
interesting with it or I could take any
pair of things and try to make something
out of it or any triple of things and
try to make something out of and so on
so to give an example the Gutenberg
printing press is a recombination or a
combination between a winepress and
movable type the right brother airplane
is a combination between an airfoil a
light gas engine
bicycle wheels and a propeller so I just
wrote down literally the simplest
equation you can write down it just says
got the M things you got now and you got
some chance of making something useful
out of all the single things some
smaller chance of making something out
of all of the pairs of things but
there's a lot more pairs of things than
there are single things right and an
even smaller probability of making
something useful out of triplets of the
24 things but there's an awful lot of
those and this equation to something
amazing
apparently it hadn't been written down
there's now theorems about it that might
steal this burgers there's two papers on
archive but nothing published yet here's
what it does Jim so put time on the
horizontal axis and M the number of
goods on the vertical axis the this
thing goes along it had increases very
very very slowly glacially for a long
time then all of a sudden it's
skyrockets upward in a hockey stick and
most importantly it goes to infinity at
some finite time it goes vertical it's
called a pole mathematically so I hope
that was interesting and I got in touch
with a friend named Bretton Roger Koppel
you might want to talk to Roger about
he's at the University of Syracuse an
economist and Roger said it and he said
you know that looks like the Industrial
Revolution so we worked with the equate
this equation which we call ta P boldly
it's the theory of the adjacent possible
and it turns out I I'm finding this
remarkable so let's suppose over because
it actually has a societal import two
million years ago our ancestors
Australia Pittacus three million years
ago started making stone tools and they
had maybe ten really crude tools like
you know facial stone scrapers over a
couple million years not much happens
and we get to Homo erectus and Homo
habilis homo sapiens is around 300,000
years ago some homo sapien bore about
bones were just found in Greece from two
hundred ten thousand years ago not much
happens you get to cro-magnon who's oz
thirty thousand years ago they now have
a few hundred
ranging in complexity from arrowheads to
you know the atlatl it's really neat yep
yeah thrower
yeah they invented the spear throw
doesn't really complex saying it helped
a lot you could throw your spear at the
ORAC you know from 15 feet away rather
than running up to it and jabbing it
opportunity if it was something you know
bigger than an ORAC so they had a few
hundred tools ranging in complexity from
simple things to more complex things
part of what I want to convey is how
long everything cook it took a hundred
thousand years to get to cro-magnon
that's human that says that's humans
ignoring and all the tricks it takes
another eight ten thousand years to get
to agriculture when agriculture comes we
get to Mesopotamia five thousand years
ago four thousand years ago on another
tiger said you afraid
then a few thousand kinds of things
ranging from needles that have been
around for sixty thousand years to
chariots so see an increasing diversity
of things and an increasing
diversification and two simple and more
complex things all of this falls out
from this little tap equation well then
you get to us now and this process
skyrockets upward we now have billions
of goods ranging from needles to space
stations Jim nobody knows how that
happened I think this ridiculously
simple equation says it but it says more
what it says is that the more things you
got the easier it is to make yet more
things out of what you got and we are
now assuming upward almost vertically
that's why we're in the Anthropocene now
were the same species we can invent
things so trivially now we have a
hundred trillion dollar global economy
growing at 4% a year inventing ever more
new things lifting millions of people
out of poverty and invading every niche
on the planet we're destroying the
planet with our own creativity and this
simple little equation says it so it's
tap it's this process buried in it are a
couple more things you make the next
more complex thing that you make out of
the less complex things you
now you couldn't make a space station
you know until we had Rockets you
couldn't make a crossbow till you had a
bow and this little process says has
reinterpreted says the same thing it
says at any time T the last thing you
made is the most complex thing you got
the next thing you could make could be
more complex and therefore it gives rise
to an increasing number of things with
increasing differentiation it's simple
and more complex things okay so Tim
Koehler is an archaeologist who I'm now
working with Tim's look at the onset of
inequality in humans in Neolithic sites
and 67 Neolithic sites from you know 30
or 40 thousand years ago it's called the
Gini index there's already inequality
way before agriculture you find
Neolithic sites with simple graves and
to the same place there's more complex
graves I was stunned to find that in in
and in one of them I read there's three
adolescents buried and they have very
complicated necklaces around their neck
with shells from a couple hundred miles
away that tells you that thirty thousand
years ago says their adolescence there's
inheritance there's a marked
differentiation in wealth and people are
gathering shells from a couple thousand
miles away a couple hundred miles away
so do you have the onset of inheritance
inequality and the same little equation
says inequality if you can make chariots
and you can make needles people who loan
chariots have more valuable property
than people who have needles so the same
process gives rise to where as part of
giving rise to an equality and
inequality it's now one of the
overwhelming things on the planet look
at inequality in New York it's it's the
worst it's been in history go to San
Francisco and see 10,000 people living
on the street in the richest city in the
world probably you know and somehow an
awful lot of this is a consequence of
the same simple process but even more
struck me it's taking me some time this
is very said Jim it's certainly not
published but think about the big bang
so here you have the big bang and you
got quarks and gluons and stuff and the
three quarks get together it's called
heteros ation it's roughly the same
process
all that step process does is it says
take what's lying around and make new
things out of it don't have to be a
person so what happens in the early
universe is you get quarks and
antiquarks and they combine to make
protons and neutrons and electrons which
combine to make hydrogen and helium then
three helium nuclei get together to make
carbon so what happens is two helium's
get together and then make beryllium so
watch - things have gotten together to
make a new things than beryllium and
helium combined to make carbon so now
you've got the synthesis nucleus
synthesis and the stars of 100 nuclei
that are stable then you start getting
space chemistry so you've got the atoms
of organic molecule carbon hydrogen
nitrogen and so on and you start making
molecules of increasing complexity it's
roughly the same princess new things get
made out of old things and it doesn't
matter whether it's pots or ideas or
molecules it's the same wacky process
and would you take things and combine
them and I'm starting to think the
following I think if one looks at the
chemical evolution of the universe it
probably looks like tap it goes along
very very slowly for a long time
that it starts shooting upward and some
evidence for that is that meteorites the
Murchison from five billion years ago
has 35,000 organic molecules so does the
enceladus of the moon of Saturn if you
go through it's Jets have thousands of
organic molecules in a guy in Germany
I'll break up is just under an
experiment it's worth pausing over this
term do you know the miller-urey
experiment yo yes were the lightning and
the bottle and the Miller a year do this
in the 50s so they took a flask they
have water in it and carbon dioxide and
methane and ammonia I guess they were
trying to mimic the atmosphere of the
early Earth and they said electric
sparks they would tried to mimic the
early atmosphere and Miller was a young
graduates that anne-marie was a Nobel
laureate in chemistry at three days
later or four days later they had a
brown scum on the bottom of the pot they
looked at it was full of amino acids of
different kinds
and everybody was rightly excited it
said gosh look at this we can have the
synthesis out of simple things of the
building blocks of life and that started
a 40-year search to see what else you
could make that way on earth and then we
learned there's in fall two meteorites
that brought stuff too like the
Murchison well roughly in the last two
years this guy al rushed up
OTT who is at a university in Germany I
can't remember what he's done the
falling amazing experiment Jim he's
taken the miller-urey experiment and I
guess he's let it run for a month he
gets thousands of organic molecules I'm
calling it a spray well I think he's
getting what the universe has done for
the past 13 billion years molecules make
more molecules which can combine to make
more molecule to get more complex and
I'm wondering whether or not there's a
hockey stick evolution gradual for a
long time then scooting upward really
fast as the universe makes more complex
molecules so for example this means that
five billion years ago if the earth had
a soup of thirty five thousand or so
organic molecules
so did planets everywhere in the
universe how do we fly the way you could
have gotten life because they could have
been self reproducing molecular sets so
this tap thing may be catching something
really general it looks like it's
capturing something about technological
evolution about cultural evolution about
the evolution of the chemistry of the
universe it's so simple you just take
what you got and combine it and see what
new you can make out of it do you have
to have a pruning rule which is that
many in fact most combinations make no
sense right have no utility and you know
the generative nough subtly existing set
is highly dependent upon the the rule
which combinations make sense and which
ones don't and it's certainly possible
to have a transition matrix in which the
result is only minimal increase in
complexity over time why let's hold
right there so let's get to economics
which is what you're talking about right
now I'm not sure that that applies to
molecules I don't know I mean there's
going to be some stability for different
molecules one way of asking it is to
take this out break
our system and say what does this look
like over time I don't know that
Albert's looked at it one could look at
it in fact a group of this is trying to
get money from CERN to look at just that
so now let's take the economy so you're
right so my old example is I take a
parachute and I put it over the stack of
the Queen Mary and you just get a mess
but if you put it at the back of an
airplane and it pops up when the
airplanes lands you made an air break so
only some combinations will produce
something useful for a given task I mean
maybe you want to put it over the
smokestack of the Queen Mary for some
stupid task only some combinations will
prove useful and that's actually already
in this little equation it says out of
all the possible subsets of three things
out of a thousand which is something
like a thousand times a thousand times a
thousand which is I guess a billion only
a modestly small subset will be useful
for any particular thing so one of the
ways I think about this this is like
jury-rigging would you rather
jury-rigged with a garage full of junk
or almost nothing well you'd rather do
it with a garage full of things because
if you got a bunch of stuff out there I
said technically you'll find something
to jury-rig do lots of different things
that's real technical talk but it's true
your rigging is not algorithmic it's we
just go do it and indeed it certainly
speaks the most common sense and basic
quantitative analysis that the more more
components you have to try to I'm more
likely you are to find something that
actually does make sense right but the
thing that I'd like us to just pause
over Jim we really are in the
Anthropocene we are living in a hundred
trillion global economy it really is
growing at 4% a year
it really is lifting millions of people
out of poverty in China for example
right now and it really is invading
every niche on the planet did you see
the UN report about extinction events oh
yes the two came out a couple of months
ago then it's expected by 2050 20% of
all species is going to be extinct a
million species what are we doing to the
bio sir
we're eradicating it you can recover
from global warming which is a
catastrophe in thousands of years
recovering from a mass extinction event
as millions of years we have no idea
what we're doing with didn't parent I
don't even know how to say chip what can
you imagine that will slow down this
juggernaut of an expanding economy
inventing ever new things doing evermore
huge projects decimating love and
certainly we're getting close to the
edge I mean to my favorite scary
statistics are the mass of humans and
their domestic animals mostly cattle in
terms of actual weight is now something
like 60% of all large mammals on earth
that's absurd
right and it's and for birds the numbers
even higher the weight of all birds in
the world is utterly dominated by
domestic fowl under that rule yes I
couldn't believe it when I read that so
I've researched and found it referenced
in multiple places Jim it's terrifying
that something really struck me we
debate whether humans are having an
impact on the globe so just think of
this
so 35,000 years ago there's cro-magnon
and they're living in the caves of the
door down on the north Oh Fran in Spain
and they're there for 15,000 years and
they paint the walls of the caves and
they go from you know a few hundred
kinds of tools to a few hundred kinds of
tools and then some of them migrate
north when the ice sheets go away and
the guys in the north of Spain I guess
stay there and go clam fishing or
whatever for ten thousand years or
fifteen thousand years there are they're
there they're the same species and
nothing much changes two things my
father was born in 1903 I'm getting at
the rate of change and it's bigger D
into the fact that the more stuff you
got the more stuff you can make in the
same period of time right so my dad was
born in 1903 my son was born in 1969 my
dad was born the year flight was
invented my son was born sixty-six years
later when we landed on the moon the
pace of change is enormous because we
can make so many things so fast now for
the impact on the planet so I'm I'm 80
gosh cos I was born in 1939
I grew up with milk being delivered in
milk bottles in the graduate Dustin
Hoffman is famously told think plastics
well plastics was a big thing in 1960
sixty years later 2020 we have crashed
our oceans and our sea shores all around
the planet with gargantuan piles of
plastic crap that will not decay in
thousands of years and we're making more
of it have we affected the planet at 16
years
well there's masses of plastics floating
in the oceans then we didn't even have
plastic 60 years ago so let's not debate
the fact that humanity's impacting the
planet we're overwhelming of it and it
were not being mean nobody's
mean-spirited it's not capitalism it is
the inventiveness of the tap process in
which we inevitably invent more things
that are useful for stuff but we just
keep doing it if it's inevitable and you
know the tap equation at least says the
jacent possible will exponentially
increase over time how do we get out of
that is there is there any way to get
out of it or we are gonna just go up
against the limits and crash tap if it's
fundamental would indicate that might be
what happens Jim it's worse than
exponential an exponential never reaches
infinity in finite time this thing goes
vertical it reaches infinity and finite
time I think we are now going steeply up
this is curved and this is the
Anthropocene and what we confront you
know one could say this and you know
it's so stark what we're confronting is
global and what we're confronting is
civilizational this is our own humanity
creating and creating and we're
wonderful at it we've been doing it for
three million years overwhelming the
planet this image came to be a couple of
weeks ago you know Easter Island
so there's Easter Island of this the
stone figures facing east it's an island
out in the middle of the ocean
what did the person who cut down the
last tree think well the earth is an
island in space Jim were cutting down
the last tree
we have to find a way of becoming aware
of this as a species with all of our
interesting
identity politics and Muslims versus
Jews versus Hindus versus whatever and
the civilizational goods and Bad's of
the global civilization emerging ends if
conceivable make some transformation in
which we find valuable human lives when
we are of nature not above it Western
society there's this amazing line by
Francis Bacon in about 1660 the West is
just turning to look at the real world
if this is the start of empirical
science and bacon says I take all
knowledge to be my province which was
easier than their woman's much then he
roughly says didn't quite say this but
it says meaning to put nature on the
rack and rest our do
well that's center of extractive
modernity and it works within the
context of the rules of modernity the
problem is we've now reached the limits
and our social operating system seems to
have no way to constrain itself that's
right
it's overwhelming Jim I'm living in a
beautiful house in Santa Fe with with
Kate and it's got all the conveniences
and as as a Jeffery West says enough
energy per person to be a thousand
slaves and we're already comfortable we
have it's a species of planetary species
essentially to become aware of the
implications of this type thing that I
wrote down two years ago that's why it's
happening it's not mal-intent
we're no different in our intent than
people were 40,000 years ago not much
happen for thousands of years with the
same emotional structure then as now
it's just that we can create so much out
of what we've created that we keep
creating we're gonna die by our own
creativity as we were talking about
earlier before we went on the air
there's something charming about life in
America in the 18th century and the
energy density was vastly lower we would
not be destroying the planet if we had
somehow found a way to say stop right
what
in 1840 was we were on the we were on
the frontier of the Industrial
Revolution and we've exploded since then
and a per capita GDP has gone up faster
than population growth can so population
for the first time in history it started
exploding a couple of centuries ago most
seven billion people now because per
capita GDP is going up faster than
population when you multiply the two
together you're at least in a rough
order the load on the ecosystem and as
we were just saying it's we've got to be
getting close to the limits and the
operating system itself has no means to
correct itself at least it's very very
difficult in my own work in politics I
analyze the engine of money on money
return it's now become Unleashed from
human control you know everybody dances
to money and money corrupts politics
until we learn to develop a new social
signaling network or constrain the power
of money it's not obvious to me how we
can stop this beast driving us right
over the cliff I think you're right it's
driving us over to cliffs it's certainly
that the rich get richer you know the
top one percent the top tenth of a
percent
have you seen Thomas Piketty discussion
of this in my read capital and I've read
some of his more recent articles well
I've only read about capital but I think
I understand it
his basic idea with respect to this is a
tax that just taxes people on big
estates take any estate over 50 million
and take away 2% of it every year and
put it into a general pot well that
would do it it's good he'll never pass
but that would do it in a sense
Elizabeth Warren's doing that or
proposing that but Jim that won't do
anything about the fact that we're
inventing ever new things and processes
and wished to make bubblegum and purple
plastic penguins for the pool side and
apps and new kinds of penicillin and new
kinds of gadgets and new kinds of vast
projects like the Silk Road that the
Chinese are doing now that is just going
to keep invading the planet even if we
were to distribute the money better and
help inequality what's gonna slow down
the juggernaut that's growing and here's
the part that a lot of people have not
caught
which is not only do we have this tap
driven faster than exponential wave of
new products most of which we don't need
or want probably but the money on money
return machine drives the
psychologically informed marketing to
invent new needs for you right well yes
but but pause there's the inventing of
new needs since it was the guy been a
you know who was a the the nephew of
Freud and my son you know he invented in
about 1920 advertising and cigarettes or
freedom candles or something but it's
more in dodging so that if you invent a
screw it meets its complement the
screwdriver to be useful so goods in the
economy call forth the invention of
still more new goods that are the
complements or substitutes of existing
goods so once you got cellphones you get
apps with once you've got rockets you
get the space station advertising as a
piece of it but this has been going on
since long before advertising let's turn
up you made a big point of that in your
book that complementarity by itself a
draws forth the future right especially
in the economy by the way it's time to
mention Brian Arthur Bryant's book the
nature of Technology 2009 talks about
lots of this Brian we're old friends
Brian doesn't have this equation but
he's got lots of the central tenets and
is you should really read the book
good night not only did I read the book
I actually read some of the chapters
before it was published and gave him
some feedback on it oh great
Brian and I were actually office mates
when I was at full-time at the Institute
back in 2002 to 2004 oh really
yeah so yes I'm very familiar with that
book that's a must read for anybody
that's thinking in these in these areas
and that book got less attention that it
should really I mean that is one of the
most profound books on network models of
one important part of the economy which
is the evolution of technologically
driven products and businesses I think I
agree with Brian set the foundation and
the stuff I'm talking about that grows
out of it there's not a bunch of there's
some you know Brian's doing it too
O'Brien even gets to the idea well I did
too and I guess in 1998 Brian and I were
friends at the early age we kept going
to babes for lunch it was really cute
because we'd go to babes and Brian would
order fish stew and each time he'd say
this fish do is just terrible and he
keep ordering three kids anyway Brian
taught me some economics said I wrote a
paper in 1988 about it actually I wanted
Brian to be a co-author but for some
reason he didn't want to be didn't
happen so once you start thinking about
things making things it's growing on me
how simple it is suppose that you have a
number of things in and in general two
things can get together and making new
things okay I'd like to what we're
talking about then the differential
equation for the number of things is DN
DT is equal to n times N or N squared
even I can integrate it that means that
and and I've checked it with it with
regard so like so if you integrated DN
DT is equal to K N squared if you
integrate it as n is equal to n to the
third per time and that's hyperbolic it
goes infinite times - yeah but yeah
once you've got a general process that
takes pairs of things that makes new
things out of it and you can sample
pretty much the things that are around
now there's a process it looks like it's
going to reach infinity in finite time
well point out again the fecundity
filter makes it go not that fast because
not all not all the combinations work in
fact the combinations at work are quite
sparse and if they're sparse enough it
changes from a hyperbolic to a parabolic
or even to a super linear the national
theorems that bike still has produced in
a paper that we've got online this
process is hyperbolic but the model
doesn't have it that things die right
things fail or combinations fail yeah so
if you put into the things just go away
so things could just drop out or any
moment so call that view then if mu is 0
goes to infinity a theorem if you use a
little greater than zero it either goes
to infinity or or it goes to zero at
finite time
some probability so we know a little bit
about that that's still not adequate
because things don't die alone when one
thing dies a bunch of other things die
within Schumpeterian guilds of creative
instruction and we don't know very much
about that yet well this has been
amazingly interesting back and forth
about all kinds of cool things but we've
gone a long way from your book you know
one of the cores of your book is the I
took it way as the point point of your
book was origin of life why don't we
talk about what you think about the
origin of life today after having
studied it for lo these many years it's
so fascinating Jim let me tell you how
its it's interesting how the problem
arose before about the middle 1900s
there was no problem about the origin of
life if you looked at a rotten log after
a rain you know there were maggots so
they obviously had sprung forth from the
from the rotten lug
now then hardik who's just written a
review of the early of the orc send it
to you you know finds us what wonderful
thing in which there's some doctor in
1740 who says that if you take a piece
of cloth that is laden with sweat from
your armpit and you mix it with wheat
and you put it in a box a mousehole
emerge okay so what happened is that in
somewhere in the late nineteen hundreds
of mid nineteen hundreds there was a
prize set by the French people now had
microscopes and they were making wine
ads on they found that if you put a
broth out a couple they said it was all
milky and was full of bacteria and the
question was was this spontaneous life
so Pasteur did a brilliant simple
experiment and the neck is s-shaped that
comes comes up and down then up and he
filled the neck words down with water so
air couldn't get in from the outside
here to the sterile flask and ten days
later there was no bacteria in it so
after a very finding or a foie gras and
Luca Daniel people wrote differently he
says life only comes from life well
that's right but then the question comes
the where did life come from the pester
sets the problem of the origin of life
in 1870 or whenever basically nothing
happened around nineteen
and halt dein and upper and operon and
russia and holiday and start to think
about my operon says there's going to be
coacervate sore little jaunt like things
in the early Earth and somehow they're
gonna have complex chemical mixtures and
life's going to happen and halt dein
comes up with the idea of a primitive
soup in which those kinds of organic
molecules in the ocean so for many years
origin of life talks often had somebody
with some Campbell Soup can label
primitive soup then Miller and Urey come
along in the 50s so they show you know
you already can make amino acids out of
just the atmosphere and organ life were
sort of exploded then and for around
twenty or thirty years even now people
are showing that out of beginning things
you can make things like sugars and
nucleotides and lipids and so on people
don't know yet about this guy Abra
coughs result with the spray I don't
know why he's not getting more attention
it's amazing so you wait for a month and
you get thousands of organic molecules
so then what happened in the origin of
life field is by 1954 we know about DNA
replication is Watson incorrect so what
I was coming into biology around 63 or
64 the obviously about the origin of
life was DNA as a double helix it
specifies its own sequence those RNA you
can make a double helix of RNA and
everybody had the a idea take a single
strand of RNA a ucg some salt long
polymer call it the watson strand will
it please line up free nucleotides that
will make this bind to the watson strand
so you've got a bunch of free
nucleotides and then something links
them together and now you've got the
Crick strand with its complement they
melt a part in cycle and that's all life
started and that's a perfectly
reasonable idea it's a fine idea
less than a argue and others have tried
to do it for 50 years the experiment
doesn't work it should but it doesn't
and the reasons are sort of chemical if
the replicated strand is full of G's
Nazis it folds up in little knots and
precipitates and DNA and RNA have three
prime five prime phosphate ester bonds
but thermodynamically they'd rather do
two prime v from the quick summary is
all the years laters nobody's made at
work so pause it's still the dominant
view and it became even more dominant in
I guess 1986 the ribozymes had been
discovered these are RNA molecules that
catalyze reactions and while I Gilbert
published an article in Nature said we
can conceive of a world just with RNA
molecules let's call it the RNA well
that view is dominated and what is
dominated in that view of life is
template replicating RNA and it might
work someday and people are trying to
make it work then hornik I'll send you
is he's just written an article that
came out in biological theory literally
today
so then it's traced the history of the
theory of auto catalytic cents which
actually I started and published in 71
but that idea is that I catalyze the
formation of you out of two jim parts
and you catalyze the formation of bill
out of to develop parts and bill
catalyzes the formation of stew out of
stupor
it's a mutually autocad except nobody
catalyzes information so there's been a
lot of work started by me I guess in
1971 then in 1986 with some theorems
it's a work done with don't farmer and
norm Packard that you really could get
these systems fundamentally if you get
it complicated enough system it'll
spontaneously make auto catalytic sets
so that was theory for some time then
real ones were made so good new front
caderousse key made the first auto
catalytic set out of DNA in 94 in about
95 residue Deary at Scripps made the
first self-reproducing protein he took a
protein sequence like 32 amino acids
that's an alpha helix that coils back on
itself making coiled coil and he
reasoned as they say after the fact that
if he took the two fragments 15 and 17
long
true fragments would bind to the 32
Marin and go together and he'd get the
32 mer to reproduce itself well it does
within a few years gone on ashkenazi now
in the ben-gurion had made a nine
peptide collectively Auto kind of accept
pause that tells you that molecular
reproduction absolutely does not depend
on template replicating DNA or RNA
it just doesn't so that happened
experimentally then I told you that I
think they were about 2012 now Salim and
and vitae published an article in Nature
I think was at that time the most
important experiment on the origin of
life they took some ribozymes
and chop them in half where ribozyme a
chopped in half could glue together with
one of the halves of chopped a be
chopped in half and they put it in a pot
and it spontaneously went collectively
autocannon sets of ribosomes so that was
superb except that that so one good a
spontaneous formation of collectively
unaccounted sets and a bunch of us are
writing about that now but they're still
using evolve molecules so what we want
to know is if you take random polymers
can you make autocad make sense there's
hints that you can it's possible the
fellow named Lee Cronin is doing
not at liberty to tell you the details
yes and publish it yet we have this
money I told you about to try to do it
from from CERN and I told you the next
most important thing that's happened is
Johanna is Xavier and Bill Martin and a
paper still not published Mike Steel
then Hornick on the paper I'm a
co-author but I did nothing much on the
paper except they put my name on it I
thank them they have found this
metabolic autocatalytic said where no
polymers in it at all so it's almost
sure now that life started in a rich
soup of organic molecules everywhere in
the universe around 5 billion years ago
what's missing Jim is how hard is it to
get an autocatalytic set and a bunch of
small molecules and totally unpublished
Mike steel is just proving theorems
right now that it should be pretty easy
and if so we might be able to detect it
pretty soon experimental e and so I've
got significant dreams that we could do
that the group of us that's gotten money
from CERN is meeting soon and maybe will
think is possible figured out and
suppose that works so you got molecular
reproduction five billion years ago all
over the universe because the universe
has cooked up this stuff well so now you
got this metabolic autocatalytic said
you'd like to get some polymers going
how would you glued the two together so
you had that polymers catalyzing the
reactions of the metabolism how do you
put the thing in a liposome that I told
you about Roberto sara has shown they
will synchronize the division of the
molecular system in the auto County and
the polymer system so can we actually
make protocells and the reason we're new
feature well maybe people always say
it's around the corner then it's not so
maybe we can that's huge as we can do it
it's all isn't loose in science how does
life emerge
maybe he's it's sort of a process of tap
and auto catalysis maybe let me push
back just a little bit can I've been
following this for many many years spent
time talking to norm Packard I spent
time talking to you back when I was at
SFI the one part of it that I have a
time getting my head around and over is
that these earlier prebiotic chemical
regimes are not by any means high
fidelity replicators and we know we know
from mathematically in evolutionary
theory there's something called the
error catastrophe that if the fidelity
of copying is not greater than X and X
is actually a pretty crisp number for
any well-defined system ability to
ratchet evolution is surprisingly small
entropy quickly breaks down what
evolution builds up and these are all
low fidelity replicators and yet our
world the world of all life that we know
is built on a high fidelity replicator
its DNA plus replication plus error
correction which appears at least
empirically to be well past the error
catastrophe stage so how in the world
does this free life protocell chemistry
world ratchet itself up with worse than
era catastrophe driven evolution to
create high fidelity information
transfer and if we can't do that we
don't actually get life as we know it
other short answers you're right chimp
so here's sort of what we know what I've
told you does not get us to RNA template
replication or DNA template replication
or coding of encoded proteins is where
the deep mystery is proteins that are
encoded are the amino acids synthetases
that translate the code there's some
chicken and egg problem that's huge how
did that ever emerge and we we don't
know Peter wills is working out a lot of
people have worked on it for a long time
it's not cracked yet there's some ideas
so I had David Deamer and others can fit
right in and have little protocell
floating around without any DNA or RNA
or you could put DNA in RNA you can make
an autocratic set out of RNA now it's
lame and did years ago the question is
how do you get to something like
template replicating DNA and RNA then
actually Paul Davies rightly points out
in his book on the origin I've called
the demon in the Machine the the
ribosome plus the
code is in von Neumann sensei Universal
constructor it can make any protein out
of the standard 20 amino acids that's
amazing and just imagine what it left
for the origin of life of that happened
you could explore protein space
trivially just by you know making
proteins so there's some ideas about how
the code could have emerged I even have
some ideas out of the codes have emerged
then I'm not competent to talk about it
you should talk to people wills it is
clear that these Auto counting systems
can evolve without encoded protein
synthesis and the reason is do basically
to might steal and and dim Hornick I'll
send you the link that they just sent me
that them to send me these article came
out today an autocatalytic set is made
up of a large network irreducible
autocatalytic sets and first rough marry
led a group of us to show that these
irreducible odd occurrences could be
gained and lost the little replicating
systems and they're acting like genes
animal evolution from that and as don
farmer and and ragga show years ago you
can imagine that unkennel has reactions
happen they can be captured by the
system and the system can evolve to some
extent not like you can't with encoded
proteins we've got it there's no talk of
energy in all of this yet either if you
put things through a wet/dry cycle it's
called the plasting reaction I was
writing about it in 1993 Dave Deemer and
Bruce Damer are focusing on it now
dehydrating and rehydrating the life of
some is adding energy to the system and
people are finding Dave dealers got some
wonderful things about the onset of
transport across membranes he's in Santa
Cruz he's really worth talking to you
it's not there yet Jim but it's not as
far away as it was interesting one of
the topics we talk about a lot on this
show is the Fermi paradox where are they
right and you know the called the
Stewart Kaufmann view life's probably
ubiquitous right there's 22 stars in the
universe it's not less debated that
something like half of them have holders
solar systems so it's 10 to the 22 solar
systems suppose one in a thousand of
them have life so that's 10 to the 19th
bias years out
that's a lot of biases if it turns out
the true life was easily reachable
across this information gap this error
catastrophe gap and you know when I was
a 14 year old nerd I would have bet any
sum of money that I had which wasn't
much that there was lots of intelligent
species out there but the more I've
thought about it hard read on the Fermi
paradox the various Prudy rules it's
possible we might be the only one right
but turns out this gap is unbelievably
hard at low probability we hard and low
possibility you're right but if there's
if by my crude calculation there's 10 to
the 20th biospheres out there then for
there to be none it's gonna have to be
really small compared to 10 to the 20 10
to the 20 prebiotic autocatalytic
metabolism works just waiting for
something like yes this is where I've
come out is that Stuart Kaufman is
correct that probably there is a
unbelievably large number of integrated
auto catalytic and metabolic networks
yeah and inside of you know fat but all
that question is how what percentage of
them ratchet up so having high fidelity
information transfer until we have some
understanding about how hard it is to
get to template replicating DNA or in it
or some other molecule to compari we're
really talking about Schrodinger's what
is life in a periodic solid of which DNA
and re are the wonderful examples that
could carry as he says a micro code for
the organism which DNA does until we
know how that happens and the micro code
is reliably transferred we don't know
but it can't be that far away Jim we'll
find out as people are working on it I
still remain agnostic right but I will
say I now give fair credit to those who
say that that leap may be so damn hard
it only happened one if that is true
this talk we've had earlier about to
destroy our ecosystem is even more Wow
it's even more morally it's morally
loaded right if we're the only life in
the universe and one could say perhaps
our destiny is to bring the universe to
life if we snuff
intelligent like it'll not be good well
I think some bacteria will survive yeah
I think they will to it and probably
even other animals but will they get
back to intelligence cockroaches will
make it cockroaches we always have with
us Thank You Stuart this has been great
we've had a few technical difficulties
the audio is not going to be as good as
it usually is but man what a great
conversation and that's the important
thing we all have to think about what
tap means for the Anthropocene and what
we're going to do as a species
everything else is trivial yeah yeah
it's interesting this the idea of tap if
you actually express tap without the
equation in your book right you talked
about this combinatoric unfolding of
both life and economy but once you have
the equation it actually is more stark
it in our face that unless we figure out
how to stop tap we're going to just run
outside all them out of the borders of
every resource and crush our planet
probably in the next hundred years
I think that's roughly right you we are
chopping down the last tree yeah that is
an unpleasant thought what has to start
happening Jim as we as a species have to
take on what this means and that is so
we're beyond anything we can say
fortunately there's some people working
on that some of the people I've
interviewed on the show will be
interviewing on the show what is the
operating system of the future look like
that has the attributes of allowing us
to have an interesting intellectually
probing species yet not destroy our
planet I will say nobody has solved that
equation yet but there are people
working on it I want to hear more from
the advantages thank you I'm hoarse this
bye bye take care be good
production services and audio editing by
Jared Jane's Consulting LLC music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]